欢迎来到我们在线课程“机器人入门”的最后一堂课。祝贺
Welcome to the very last lecture in our online course, Introduction to Robotics. Congratulations
对于那些已经做到这一点的人。
to those of you who have made it this far.
我想在这个特定的讲座中做一些不同的事情，或者说更少
I want to do something a bit different in this particular lecture and talk perhaps less
关于技术和算法，以及软件等，并进入一些可能更大的
about technology and algorithms, and software and so on, and get into some perhaps bigger
关于机器人以及它们适合社会的地方的想法。为何机器人很重要。
picture ideas about robots and where they fit into society. Why robots are important.
现在，就像我说的那样，这是一段相当长的旅程。我们谈过机器人的历史，
Now, It's been, as I say, quite a journey. We've talked about the history of robots,
在这种情况下，人类对生物体形象的建构着迷
mankind's fascination with building things in the image of living organisms, in this
案例，几百年前着名的消化鸭。我们已经谈过了
case, the famous digesting duck from many hundreds of years ago. We've talked about
对自动机的迷恋。这些栩栩如生的机器能够合理地完成
fascination with automata. These lifelike machines which were able to do reasonably
按照当天的标准执行复杂的任务。例如，一个人的小雕像
complex tasks by the standards of the day. For instance, a figurine of a person with
机械内脏能够做很复杂的图纸。例如，绘图
mechanical innards that was able to do quite complex drawings. For instance, the drawing
这是一艘船。这是从1800年代开始的。
here of a ship. And this is from the 1800's.
然后，围绕第二次世界大战的技术开始以非常快的速度发展，并且
And then, around the Second World War technology started to evolve at a very rapid rate, and
这种技术-真的是机器人的先驱。操纵系统允许科学家
this sort of technology - really the precursor of robots. Manipulation system allowed scientists
和工程师在远处操纵放射性物质。这真的，在我的
and engineers to manipulate radioactive material at the distance. And this is really, in my
信念，现代工业机器人的先驱技术。
belief, the sort of precursor technology to modern industrial robots.
第一批工业机器人是由该公司UnimationInc.开发的
And the first industrial robots were developed by this company Unimation Inc. which was founded
1956年，第一批产品在1960年代初投入使用。所以，这种
in 1956, first products went into service in the very early 1960's. So, this sort of
制造机器人，手臂机器人，制造东西，对我们的社会非常非常重要。
manufacturing robot, the arm robot, builds stuff, very, very important to our society.
这是一项非常古老的技术。它正在走向60年。
It's a very old technology now. It's getting on towards 60 years.
所以，我们已经谈到了机器人技术的这种演变，我们也谈到了什么
So, we've talked about this evolution of robotic technology, and we've also talked about what
使这项技术成为现实。我们已经谈到了如何建造机器人。我们已经谈过如何做了
makes this technology tick. We've talked about how to build robots. We've talked about how
我们代表工作空间中物体的姿势。我们谈到了正向运动学，
we represent the pose of objects in the work space. We've talked about forward kinematics,
反向运动学，雅可比行列式和联合控制以及刚体动力学。这些是
inverse kinematics, and Jacobians and joint control and rigid body dynamics. These are
如果你正在建立一个手臂类型，所有基本原则都非常重要
all the fundamental principles that are really important if you are building an arm type
机器人。这些是我们自这项技术以来60年来所学到的东西
robot. These are the things that we've learnt in this 60 years since this technology was
第一个构思。技术首先是理论，我们的数学
first conceived. The technology came first and the theory, the mathematics that we've
得知，后来来了。
learned about, came later.
这些机器人对现代工业非常重要。这是一张这样的照片
These robots are really important to modern industry. Here’s a picture of this kind
机器人，建造汽车，他们还建立计算机和移动包裹
of robot, building motor cars and they also build computers and move packages around in
工厂等。今天有超过一百万的这种臂式机器人在地球上工作。
factories and so on. There's more than a million of these arm type robot and work on planet Earth today.
最近有一类新的机器人。我们称之为服务机器人或现场机器人。
More recently there is this new class of robots. We call them service robots or field robots.
而且，这是服务机器人的一个例子。这是一个为a执行服务的机器人
And, this is an example of a service robot. It's a robot that performs a service to a
人。在这个特殊情况下，这项服务是清洁我的地板。而这些机器人
human being. And this service in this particular case is cleaning my floor. And these robots
已经变得非常受欢迎，超过1000万的这些机器人出售。这些只是
have become phenomenally popular, more than 10 million of these robots sold. These only
已经存在了大约十年。制造机器人几乎已经存在
have been around for only about a decade. Manufacturing robot had been around for nearly
60年。其中只有一百万。在短短10多年里，我们有1000万
60 years. There's only a million of them. In just 10 over years, we have 10 millions
这些。原因是这些机器人比制造机器人便宜得多。
of these. And the reasons are that these robots are much cheaper than the manufacturing robots.
一个人可以买得起的东西，一个人想拥有的东西，因为它提供了
The sort of thing that a person can afford, a person would like to have, because it provides
真正的价值。它在房子周围执行一项非常有用的任务。
real value. It performs a greatly useful task around the house.
所以，这是机器人的未来。会有机器人可以使用
So, this is very much the future of robots. There's going to be robots that work with
我们这是一个低成本和有用的。当然，将来会有很多其他的
us that are low cost and useful. Of course in the future, there's going to be many other
各种机器人。也许是我们将要集体遇到的下一种机器人，我
sorts of robot. Perhaps the next sort of robot that we are going to encounter en masse, I
认为这将是自驾车。谷歌自驾车项目已经实现
think it's going to be the self driving car. The Google self driving car project has got
很多媒体，所有主要的汽车公司都在研究自动驾驶汽车。
a lot of press, and all of the major automotive companies are working on self driving cars.
这是一项有些人认为可能在2020年之前实现的技术。时间
And this is a technology some people believe it might be with this by the year 2020. Time
会告诉。但我相信，这是我们日常遇到的下一个机器人技术。
will tell. But I believe, this is the next robot technology we all encounter on an everyday basis.
那么，机器人为什么呢？在世界上拥有机器人的重要原因是什么？我想
So, why robots? What's the big picture reason for having robots in the world? And I think
如果你看看我们这个星球现在面临的重大问题，主要来自人口
if you look at the big problems that our planet faces right now, come primarily from population
生长。如果我们看看未来几十年人口增长将会发生什么，那又是什么呢
growth. If we look what population growth is going to do over the coming decades, what
你可以在这张幻灯片上看到这是机器人人口的预测。到2020年，
you can see on this slide here is a prediction of robot population. And by the year 2020,
它相信这个星球上将会有一亿个机器人在工作。
its believed that there will be a hundred million robots at work on the planet.
现在，并非所有这些都将成为经典的制造机器人。许多人
Now, not all of these are going to be the classic manufacturing robots. Many of them
将会是机器人汽车，或机器人真空吸尘器，也许是机器人园丁，
are going to be for instance robot cars, or robot vacuum cleaners, perhaps robot gardeners,
机器人女佣，谁知道什么。但这是一种正在兴起的新型机器人
robot maids, who knows what. But this is the sort of new class of robot that's emerging
而且这些数量正在增加，也许是指数增长。
and the number of these is just going to increase, perhaps exponentially.
我现在要做的是谈谈我认为我们需要的大局
What I want to do now is talk about the big picture reasons why I believe that we need
机器人。这张照片说明了现在社会面临的一些重大问题，
robots. This picture illustrates some of the big problems that are facing society now,
并且在未来几十年中越来越我们面临的问题是人口增加
and increasingly in coming decades. The problems that we face are due to increased human population
在这个星球上。这个星球上有更多的人。这意味着，我们需要提供更多
on the planet. There are more people in the planet. It means, we need to provide more
餐饮。这将需要更多的运输要求。会有更多的汽车
food. This is going to require more transport requirement. There's going to be more cars
在路上，更多的人，更多的东西从一个地方到另一个地方。而这个人口
on the road, more people, more things going from one place to another. And this population
我们的年龄越来越大，需要更多的医疗保健。
of ours gets older there's going to be a need for more health care.
随着人口老龄化，我们将会出现年龄比例的不平衡。有
As the population get's older, we are going to have an imbalance in the age ratios. There's
将会有更多老年人和更少年轻人来支持他们。这是一个问题
going to be more older people and less younger people to support them. And this is a problem
这就是今天几乎所有国家都面临的问题。这是一个非常深刻的问题。
that is confronting almost country on the planet today. And it is very profound problem.
我认为我们没有真正处理好的解决方案，而是我们要做的事情
I think we don't really have handle, a good solution, on what we are going to do about
那。但我相信机器人可以在这里发挥重要作用。
that. But I believe the robots can play an important role here.
我们面临的另一个问题是气候变化。随着我们星球的气候变化，
The other problem that we are facing is climate change. As the climate of our planet changes,
它会对人们居住在哪里的水量产生真正的影响
it's going to have real impacts on where people are able to live where the amount of water
那将是可用的，以及我们可以生产的食物量。所以，非常大的图片
that would be available, and the amount of food that we can produce. So, very big picture
问题，非常复杂，所有相互关联。而且我相信机器人可以发挥很大的作用
problems, very complex and all interrelated. And I believe that robots can play a very
在改善其中一些问题方面发挥了积极作用。这就是我想谈的内容
positive role in ameliorating some of these problems. And that's what I want to talk about
在这个特别的讲座中。
in this particular lecture.
我想在本次讲座中讨论另一件事，我认为这很重要
The other thing that I want to talk about in this lecture, and I think it's an important
一，是机器人技术的伦理考虑。现在，我不是一个伦理学家，我是一个
one, is the ethical considerations around robotics. Now, I'm not an ethicist, I'm a
机器人专家。我将在本讲座后期与一位伦理学家交谈并尝试
roboticist. And I’m going to talk to an ethicist later in this lecture and just try
并解开一些适用于机器人技术的道德问题。
and unpack what are some of the issues about ethics that apply to robotics.
我们将进行讨论，我们将做一些道德操守101，学习
We are going to have a discussion, we’re going to do a bit of an ethics 101, learn
一些道德的基本原则，然后看看诸如此类的问题;是否合适
some fundamental principles of ethics, and then look at issues such as; is it appropriate
机器人照顾老人或年轻人;什么是道德问题
for robots to look after elderly people or young people; what are the ethical issues
机器人在我们的道路上驾驶汽车;侵犯隐私的问题是什么？
with robots driving cars on our roads; what are the issues around invasion of privacy;
工作中的机器人怎么样？每当我谈论机器人时，有人会问这个问题，
what about robots in jobs. Every time I give a talk about robots, somebody asks the question,
“机器人不是要带走工作吗？”我不认为这很简单。
"Aren’t robots going to take away jobs?" I don't think it’s that simple.
在本讲座中，我们想解开其中的一些问题，并详细讨论它们。
And in this lecture, we’d like to unpack some of these issues, talk about them at length.
争论，至少给你一些思考的东西。我认为这对我们很重要
At least give you something to think about, argue about. I think it's important that we
有这个特别的对话。
have this particular conversation.